<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Right rejoycing: or The nature and order of rational and warrantable joy. Discovered in a sermon preached at St. Pauls before the Lord Maior and aldermen, and the several companies of the City of London, on May 10. 1660. appointed by both Houses of Parliament, to be a day of solemn thanksgiving for Gods raising up and succeeding his Excellency, and other instruments, in order to his Majesites restoration, and the settlement of these nations. By Richard Baxter.</title>
            <author>Baxter, Richard, 1615-1691.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 97KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 30 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A76205</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867633</idno>
  <idno type="VID">119952</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240944847</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing B1377</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1025_11</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208706</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867633</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99867633e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A76205)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119952)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 152:E1025[11])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Right rejoycing: or The nature and order of rational and warrantable joy. Discovered in a sermon preached at St. Pauls before the Lord Maior and aldermen, and the several companies of the City of London, on May 10. 1660. appointed by both Houses of Parliament, to be a day of solemn thanksgiving for Gods raising up and succeeding his Excellency, and other instruments, in order to his Majesites restoration, and the settlement of these nations. By Richard Baxter.</title>
                  <author>Baxter, Richard, 1615-1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 51, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by R.W. and A.M. for Francis Tyton and Jane Underhil, and are to be sold at the sign of the three Daggers in Fleet-street, and at the Bible and Anchor in Pauls Church-Yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With a preliminary order to print.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May. 24".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119952:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:119952:1"/>
            <p>Right Rejoycing: OR The Nature and Order OF Rational and Warrantable Ioy.</p>
            <p>Discovered in a Sermon preached at S<seg rend="sup">t.</seg>
               <hi>Pauls</hi> before the Lord Maior and Aldermen, and the several Companies of the City of <hi>London,</hi> On <hi>May</hi> 10. 1660 appointed by both Houses of Parliament, to be a day of solemn Thanksgiving for Gods raising up and succeeding his Excellency, and other Instruments, in order to his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties restoration, and the settle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of these Nations.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Richard Baxter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>R. W.</hi> and <hi>A. M.</hi> for <hi>Francis Tyton</hi> and <hi>Jane Underhil,</hi> and are to be sold at the sign of the three Daggers in <hi>Fleet-street,</hi> and at the Bible and Anchor in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-Yard, 1660.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="order">
            <pb facs="tcp:119952:2"/>
            <head>Aleyne Maior.</head>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Martis 15<seg rend="sup">o.</seg> die</hi> Maii 1660. <hi>Annoque Regis Caroli Angliae,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>duodecimo.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>IT is ordered That M<seg rend="sup">r.</seg>
               <hi>Baxter</hi> be from this Court desired to Print his late Sermon at <hi>Pauls.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Sadler.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:119952:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:119952:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:119952:3"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable <hi>Thomas Aleyne</hi> Lord Maior of the City of <hi>London,</hi> with the right Worshipfull Aldermen his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S in obedience to your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable invitation, this Sermon was first preached, and the author conscious of his great unworthiness, employed in so honourable a work; so is it your pleasure (against which my judgement must not here contest) that hath thus exposed it to the publick view. Which yet I must confess doth not engage you in the patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage of any of the crudities and imperfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions
<pb facs="tcp:119952:4"/> of this hasty work; It being the <hi>matter</hi> (which is of God) that so far prevailed for your acceptance, as to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure your pardon of the <hi>manner,</hi> which is too much my own. <hi>Rejoycing</hi> is so highly valued even by nature, that I thought it a matter of great necessity, to help to rectifie and elevate your joyes. The corruption of a thing so excellent must needs be very bad: And it being the great and durable Good, that must feed all great and durable joy: and seeing these <hi>little</hi> transitory things can cause but little and transitory delight: I thought it my duty to insist most on the greatest, on which in your meditations you must most insist: which I repent not of especially now you have given my doctrine a more loud and lasting voice; because it is only our Heavenly interest, that may be the
<pb facs="tcp:119952:4"/> matter of universal, continued delight, and so the subject may make the Sermon to be of the more universal and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed use, when a subject of less excellency and duration than heaven, would have depressed and limited the discourse as to its usefulness. And also I was forced in this (as in all these sublunary things) to estimate the Mercy in which we did all so solemnly rejoyce, but as a Means, which is so far to be valued as it condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth to its end; and is <hi>something</hi> or <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing</hi> as it relateth to Eternity. Since I placed my hopes above, and learned to live a life of faith, I never desire to know any mercy in any other form or name; nor value it on any other account: as not affecting to make such reckonings, which I daily see obliterated in grief and shame, by those that make them: and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring
<pb facs="tcp:119952:5"/> who said, that if we had known Christ himself after the flesh, henceforth we know him so no more. As it was my compassion to the phrantick merry world, and also to the self-troubling me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy Christian, and my desire metho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dically to help you in your rejoycings about the great occasions of the day, which formed this exhortation to what you heard, and chose the subject which to some might seem less suitable to the day; so if the publication may print so great and necessary a point on the hearts of any that had not the opportunity to hear, as God shall have the praise, and they the joy, so you shall have (under God) the thanks, and I the attainment of my end, which is my reward: I rest</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your servant in the work of Christ, Richard Baxter.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119952:5"/>
            <head>Right Rejoycing.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>LUKE 10. 20.</bibl>
               <q>Notwithstanding in this rejoyce not, that the spirits are subject to you; but rather rejoyce because your names are written in heaven.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable, Worshipfull, and beloved Auditors,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F any of you shall say upon the hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of my Text, that I have chosen a subject unsuitable to the occasion, and that a [<hi>Rejoice not</hi>] is out of sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son on a day of such <hi>rejoycing,</hi> they may I hope be well satisfied by that time they have considered the <hi>Reason</hi> of these words as used by Christ to his Disciples, and the <hi>greater joy</hi> that's here commanded, and so the rea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on of my choice.</p>
            <p>When Christ had sent forth his seventy Disciples, to preach the Gospel through the Cities of <hi>Judea,</hi> and to confirm it by miraculous cures, for which he endued them with power from above; upon their return, they triumph especially in this, that <hi>the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils themselves were subject to them, through the name
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:119952:6"/> of Christ, ver.</hi> 17. A mercy which Christ is so far from extenuating, that 1. He sets it forth more ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly then <hi>they,</hi> ver. 18 [<hi>I beh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ld Satan as lightning fall from heaven</hi>] 2. He promiseth them <hi>yet more</hi> of it, [<hi>giving them power to tread on Serpents and on Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions, and ov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r all the power of the enemy, and that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing should by any means hurt them.</hi>] 3. He <hi>rejoiced in Spirit,</hi> and thankfully acknowledged it to the Father himself, <hi>ver.</hi> 21.] And yet he seems here to forbid them <hi>to rejoyce in it,</hi> commanding them <hi>another joy.</hi> What! was it not a mercy to be rejoyced in? Or is there any contradiction in the words of Christ? Neither: He doth not <hi>absolutely</hi> forbid them <hi>to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in it.</hi> But he saw th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t their corruption took an advantage by it, to puff them up with pride and vain-glory, and that they favoured it too carnally, and were much taken with it, as it was a visible tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph, and honour to themselves the instruments, and too much overlook't the end and use of it. Christ therefore aggravateth the <hi>Mercy in its proper notion,</hi> as it was to the honouring of the Father and himself, and the advancement of his Kingdom, and the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of mens souls, by the confirmation of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spel, and the fall of Satan. But the <hi>shell</hi> or <hi>grosser substance</hi> of the mercy; applyed to a wrong end, and by corruption made <hi>another thing,</hi> being deprived of its proper soul, this Christ admonisheth them to keep out of their estimation and affection. He meeteth his returning messengers, rejoycing too much <hi>in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves:</hi> and this proud, inordinate, selfish joy is it that he would take from them by his caution or prohibition, [<hi>In this rejoyce not</hi>] But that they may
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:119952:6"/> see that he doth not envy them their comforts, he sheweth them cause of a <hi>greater joy,</hi> which he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oweth and commandeth them, as more suitable to his ends, and their felicity: [<hi>But rather rejoyce that your names are written in heaven.</hi>]</p>
            <p>For the better understanding of this you may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve, 1. What matter of Joy the subjection of the Devils might afford them. 2. What manner of joy they were affected with, which Christ forbad them. 3. What manner of joy it is that Christ alloweth them, when he seemeth to restrain it wholly to their heavenly interest.</p>
            <p n="1">I. No doubt, to have the Devils subject to them, was a great mercy, in which they might rejoyce: For 1. It was the <hi>Gift of Christ:</hi> and all is perfumed that hath toucht his hand. Nothing but Good can come from him that is so Good▪ by way of Gift.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It was a Gift foretold by the Prophets, as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served for the <hi>Gospel-time,</hi> that's eminently called <hi>The Kingdom of God:</hi> And an <hi>extraordinary</hi> gift in respect to the precedent and subsequent generations. It was <hi>no usual</hi> thing for men to exercise such au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority over the very Devils, as to command them to come forth, and to heal the bodies that they had long afflicted.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It was a victory over the <hi>strongest</hi> enemy, that can make more effectual resistance then the most nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous armies of poor mortals, and would laugh at your horse and arms, your fire and sword, your great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est Cannons: and cannot be expugned but by the power of the Almighty. A stronger then he must come upon him and bind him, and cast him out of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:119952:7"/> his possession, before he will surrender the Garrison, goods, and prisoners which he hath held in peace, <hi>Luke</hi> 11. 21, 22.</p>
            <p n="4">4. It was a victory over the most <hi>subtile</hi> enemy, that is not conquerable by any stratagems of humane wit.</p>
            <p n="5">5. It was a victory over the most <hi>malitious enemy:</hi> that sought more then the subversion of mens tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral peace, and by afflicting the body intended the hurting of the soul.</p>
            <p n="6">6. It was a conquest of him that had <hi>long possession,</hi> and one way or other kept in bondage the prisoners, that justice had subjected to his rage.</p>
            <p n="7">7. It was a victory exceeding honourable to Christ, whose very messengers by his name alone, could make the powers of hell submit. He that refused to be made a King, as having not a Kingdom of this world, (<hi>John</hi> 18. 36.) and that had not a place to lay his head on (<hi>Mat.</hi> 8. 22.) commanded him that had presumed to tempt him with <hi>all the Kingdoms and the glory of the world, (Mat.</hi> 4. 8, 9.) and that not only by the bare word of his mouth▪ but by the word of his me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nest, most despised Messengers, which made the people stand amazed, saying, What manner of man is this?</p>
            <p n="8">8. It was a victory tending to the successes of the Gospel, to convince the unbelieving world, and so to enlarge the Kingdom of Christ, and to save the peoples souls.</p>
            <p n="9">9. And also from so great a work, it was no small honour that accrewed to the instruments: An honour which in its proper place they might lawfully regard.</p>
            <p n="10">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:119952:7"/>10. And all this was aggravated by the congruen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the mercy, to the low despised condition of the instruments, (and of Christ himself) when they were destitute of all common advantages and means, for the carrying on of so great and necessary a work, surpassing all the strength of flesh: how seasonable was it that the Omnipotency of Heaven should then appear for them, and thus engage itself for their suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cess? So that in all this you may easily see that here was abundant mattter for a rationall warran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table joy to the Disciples.</p>
            <p n="2">II. <hi>But where then was their fault? and what was that joy which Christ forbad them. Answ.</hi> Having already told you in <hi>generall,</hi> I shall tell you more <hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly.</hi> 1. They looked too much at the matter of <hi>Dominion</hi> over the subjected and ejected Devils, and relished most delightfully the externall part. As the Jews lookt for a Messiah that should come in gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deur, and bring the Nations under his dominion; so the Disciples that had yet too much of these conceits, began to be lifted up with the expectation of some earthly glory, when they saw the powers of hell sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t, and Christ thus begin with the manifestation of his omnipotency. But the great End of these Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, they too much overlooked. They too much left out of their rejoycings, the <hi>appearances of God,</hi> the advantages of faith, the promotion of the spiritual Kingdom of Christ, and the greater mercies of the Gospel, as to themselves and others.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They took too great a share of the honour to <hi>themselves,</hi> being more affected, to see what great things <hi>they</hi> were made the instruments to accomplish,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:119952:8"/> then what honour did thereby accrew to God, and benefit to man. And thus while they arrogate too much <hi>to themselves,</hi> and withall too much over-look those <hi>higher,</hi> greater mercies, to which all their <hi>mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles</hi> were but <hi>means,</hi> they deservedly fall under Christs reproof; and he is imployed in the cure of their diseased joyes, by amputation of the superflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ities, and rectifying the irregularities, and supplying the defects, lest Satan should take possession of <hi>their souls,</hi> by carnality, selfishness and pride, when they thought they had conquered him, by dispossessing him of <hi>mens bodies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">III. By this you may understand, <hi>what joy it is that Christ alloweth and commandeth them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>As to themselves</hi> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ill the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r pride, and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease their kindl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> joy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ulness, and to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance their est<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mation o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> riches of the Gospel, and rectifie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heir judgement o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the work and Kingdom of their Lord, he calls them to mind that <hi>Higher Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,</hi> which is worthy of their <hi>greatest joy. An interest in Heav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n</hi> is another kind of mercy, then healing the sick, or casting out Devils here on earth.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In reference to <hi>his honour,</hi> he would have them <hi>first</hi> look at the <hi>Greatest of his Gifts,</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd not forget the glory which he finally intends them; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ile they are taken up with these wonders in the way. For <hi>his</hi> greatest <hi>honour</hi> ariseth from his <hi>greatest mercies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. As to the <hi>Degrees</hi> of their <hi>Rejoycing,</hi> he would not have them give the <hi>greater share</hi> to the <hi>lesser mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,</hi> but to Rejoyce so much more in their heavenly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest, as that all other joy should be as none in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parison of it. So that this [<hi>Rejoyce not in this,</hi> &amp;c.]
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:119952:8"/> is as much as if he had said [<hi>Let your Rejoycing in this power over the Devils be as nothing in comparison of your rejoycing that your names are written in heaven.</hi>] Just as he forbiddeth <hi>Care</hi> and <hi>Labour</hi> for these ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thly things, when he saith [<hi>Care not what you shall eate,</hi> &amp;c.] Mat. 6. 25. [<hi>Labour not for the meat that perisheth, but for that which endureth to everlasting life, which the Son of man will give you</hi>] John 6. 27. Our Care and Labour for earthly things, must be <hi>nothing in Comparison</hi> of the Care and Labour we are at for heaven: And so our <hi>joy,</hi> in the <hi>greatest</hi> of these <hi>out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward mercies,</hi> should be as <hi>Nothing in comparison</hi> of our joy in higher things.</p>
            <p n="4">4. As to the <hi>nature</hi> and <hi>order</hi> of the thing, he allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them <hi>no joy</hi> in this or any temporal or created thing whatsoever, but <hi>as it proceedeth from God and tendeth to him as our ultimate end:</hi> We must <hi>not Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce</hi> in our victories over Satan or any other enemy, <hi>for it self,</hi> and as our <hi>end,</hi> but as it is a <hi>means</hi> to the glory of God and mens salvation. In all which it is evident, that Christ doth but <hi>regulate</hi> and <hi>advance</hi> their joy, and calling them <hi>first</hi> to rejoyce in that which is their <hi>End</hi> and <hi>All,</hi> and animateth all their lower mercies, he then alloweth and requireth them to rejoyce, even in this, which he seemed to forbid them to rejoyce in, <hi>viz. that the Devils were subj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ct to them;</hi> so they do it in due subordination to its end.</p>
            <p>The only difficulty in the preceptive part of the text is, what's meant here by the [<hi>writing of their names in heaven</hi>] In a word the meaning is, that they are <hi>fellow Citizens of the Saints, and of the houshold of God,</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:119952:9"/> and having a <hi>room</hi> among the <hi>Saints on earth,</hi> have a <hi>title</hi> to the <hi>celestial glory.</hi> As in some well-ordered Cities there were rolls kept of the names of all the Citizens, or Free-men, as distinct from all the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour, more servile sort of subjects, and as muster-rolls are kept of the listed souldiers of the Army; so all that are Saints are <hi>enrolled Citizens of heaven,</hi> that is, <hi>are the heirs of the heavenly felicity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We are <hi>Decreed</hi> to this state before the foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the world; We are <hi>Redeemed</hi> to it by the death of Christ: but we are not <hi>actually entred</hi> into it, till we are <hi>sanctified</hi> by the Holy Ghost, and heartily en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged to God the Father, Son, and Spirit, in the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Covenant.</p>
            <p>The Doctrine of the Text is conteined in this proposition; <hi>To have our names written in Heaven, is the greatest mercy, and first and chiefly, and only for it self to be rejoyced in; which so puts the estimate on all inferiour mercies, that further then they refer to this they are not to be the matter of our joy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though we had seen the Devils subjected to our ministration, departing from the possessed when we command them in the name of Christ, and the bodies of the afflicted miraculously relieved, yet all this were not <hi>comparatively</hi> to be rejoyced in, nor as <hi>se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated</hi> from our title to the heavenly glory.</p>
            <p>When I have first given you the <hi>Reasons</hi> of the <hi>prohibition, [Rejoyce not in this</hi> and then of the <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand [but rather Rejoyce,</hi> &amp;c.] you may by fuller satisfaction about the sense and truth of the Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition, be better prepared for the further application.</p>
            <p n="1">I. <hi>Rejoyce not,</hi> though the <hi>Devils</hi> themselves were
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:119952:9"/>
               <hi>subject to you,</hi> further then as this refers to Heaven; 1. Because <hi>all these common mercies,</hi> may possibly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist with the <hi>present misery</hi> of the persons that receive them. A man may be the slave of the Devil as to his soul, when he is casting him out of another mans body. He may be conquered by his own concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piscence, that hath triumphed over many an enemy. These times have shewed it to our grief, that here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie, and pride, and ambition, and self conceit, may conquer those that have been famous for their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quests: He may be a slave to himself, that is the Master of another.</p>
            <p>And what I say of the instance in my text, you may (upon a parity or superiority of reason) all along give me leave to apply to the great occasion of the day: it being a matter of much greater glory, to conquer infernal powers then mortal enemies, and to have the Devils subject to us, then men. To be such a conquerour of men or Devils, is no sure proof of the pardon of sin, the favour of God, and saving of your souls. Alas, how many called <hi>valiant,</hi> are the basest cowards in the warfare that their everlast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing life dependeth on? How many that are renown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for their victories by men, are wretches despised and abhored by the Lord? What Christian so poor and despicable in the world, that would change his state with a <hi>Cataline</hi> or <hi>Sejanus,</hi> yea with a <hi>Cesar</hi> or <hi>Alexander</hi> if he might? Could you see the inside of a glittering gallant, or an adored Prince that is a stranger to the life of faith, what a sad disparity would you see? the vermine of the most filthy lusts continually crawling in the soul, while the body is
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:119952:10"/> set out by the most exquisite ornaments, that pride can invent and their purses can procure, for the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creasing of their esteem in the eyes of such as judge of souls by the colour and cover of the bodies. To see the same man sumptuously feasted, attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, honoured, magnified by men; and at the same time dead in sin, unacquainted with the life and comforts of believers, and under the curse and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation of the Law of God, would tell you, that such a wretch is far, from the state in which a reaso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable man is allowed to rejoyce. There are not more naked leprous souls in the world, then some that are covered with a silken, laced, painted case: Nor any more poor and sordid, then such as abound with earthly riches. And for <hi>such a one to Rejoyce,</hi> is as <hi>unseemly,</hi> as for a man to glory that his gangren'd foot hath a handsom shoo, or that his diseased pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed flesh doth suffer in the fashion, or that his wounds and ulcers are searched with a silver instrument. God sees the rottenness and filth that is within these painted sepulchres, and therefore judgeth not of them as the ignorant spectator, that seeth no further then the smoothed, polished, guilded outside. And therefore we find his language of such to differ so much from the language of the world: He calls those, poor and miserable, and blind and naked, and foolish and mad, and dead and cursed, that perhaps hear nothing lower from the world, then Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, Worshipfull, Rich and Wise; and <hi>men</hi> are <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miring</hi> them, while <hi>God</hi> is <hi>loathing</hi> them; and <hi>men applauding</hi> them, while <hi>God condemneth them.</hi> And hence it is that the servants of the Lord, do <hi>lament</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:119952:10"/> the case of those that worldlings count most <hi>happy.</hi> When <hi>Paul</hi> speaks of those, <hi>whose God is their belly, whose glory is their shame,</hi> and <hi>who mind earthly things,</hi> he doth it <hi>weeping</hi> (Phil. 3. 18, 19.) when a phre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netick sensualist would but have derided his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passionate tears, and bid him keep them for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Rejoyce not in</hi> these <hi>outward common things, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratively</hi> or <hi>for themselves,</hi> because they are not only <hi>consistent with</hi> most deplorable misery, but also are the <hi>strong and ordinary means,</hi> of <hi>making</hi> men misera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and fixing them in it, and increasing it. Many that have seemed humble, fruitful, flourishing, and stedfast while they dwelt in rhe valleys of a mean, a low, afflicted state, have proved sun-burnt, weather-beaten sinners, apostates, proud, vain-glorious and barren, when they have removed their habitations to the mountains of prosperity. Alas, we find it hard enough to be serious faithfull Christians, under the less and ordinary temptations, of a poor, or mean, or suffering condition. And should I rejoice if I were put, to pass to heaven, as a Camell must pass through a needle's eye? We have <hi>difficulties</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>now <hi>already,</hi> unless our wisdom, strength and courage, were greater to encounter them; And shall we Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joice if these <hi>difficulties</hi> be encreased to <hi>impossibilities,</hi> (as with men,) leaving us no hope but that humane impossibilities are conquerable by Divine omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency? <hi>Luk.</hi> 18 27. Is it not <hi>hard enough</hi> to have a <hi>lowly</hi> mind in a <hi>low</hi> condition? (but much more in a high?) to despise the world when the world despi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth us? to walk in heaven when faith is not inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:119952:11"/> by the noise or shews of the distracted acters of these bedlam tragadies? and to converse with our everlasting company; when we are freest from these crowds and tumults? And shall we Rejoice that we, who already stumble at a straw, have rocks of offence and mountains of difficulty cast before us? How few are advanced to higher measures of faith and holiness, by their advancements in the world? For the most part, if they seemed to have something of plain honesty and fidelity before, when they come to be <hi>advanced,</hi> its drowned in car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal policies, self-love and hypocritical dissimulation: And if they seemed before to be humble and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly, and to live to God, and to his interest and ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, how strangely doth prosperity and dignity transform them, and make them forget their former apprehensions, their convictions, purposes and vows, yea their God, their happiness, and themselves? And should we not be very cautelous how we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joice, in an air that few men have their health in? and in a diet (how sweet soever) that corrupts and kills the most that use it? in the tables that prove snares, an the sumptuous houses that are traps to the inhab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tants?</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Rejoyce not in these common things:</hi> for they are but such as are often <hi>made the Devils tools to do his his work by,</hi> and <hi>are used against the Lord that gave them,</hi> to the hindrance of the Gospel and injury of the Church of Christ. While men are <hi>low,</hi> and <hi>live by faith,</hi> they do good with the <hi>little</hi> which they have; and have the blessing of the <hi>Will</hi> (when they
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:119952:11"/> are unable for the <hi>deed,</hi>) and of hearts disposed to do <hi>good,</hi> if they <hi>had</hi> opportunity: when usually those that are lifted up, having <hi>more</hi> of <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>less</hi> of <hi>Will,</hi> do <hi>less</hi> when the <hi>might</hi> and <hi>should</hi> do <hi>more;</hi> and use their talents to aggravate their sin and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation: To <hi>further</hi> piety, or charity, they have <hi>power</hi> without <hi>will;</hi> but to <hi>hinder</hi> it, they have both <hi>power</hi> and <hi>will.</hi> And while the poor of the world, that are rich only in faith, <hi>would</hi> help on the work of God, and cannot (by the great assistances which the great might give,) and the rich and honourable <hi>can</hi> and <hi>will</hi> not, but <hi>can</hi> and <hi>will</hi> promote the interest of the flesh; you may easily see the Churches case, how sure it is to know adversity, and how much of our expectation must be from God, and how little from any of the Sons of men. Is it as common for one that is <hi>very rich</hi> to part with all to follow Christ for the hopes of heaven, as it is for one that hath not much in the world to part with? Is it as common for one that hath many thousands a year, to cast all his substance into the treasury, as for a widdow to do it that hath but two mites? <hi>Luke</hi> 21. 2, 4. O how much easier were it like to <hi>go</hi> with the Church of God, if <hi>greatness</hi> and <hi>ungodliness</hi> were not no so com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly conjunct? But usually, as riches, and digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and honours do much encrease their <hi>carnal inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest,</hi> so do they encrease their <hi>carnal-mindedness,</hi> and their <hi>engagements</hi> against that life of faith &amp; holiness, which is contrary to their interest; so that none are such malignant adversaries to godliness, and none have such <hi>advantage</hi> to <hi>execute</hi> their malice. Seeing then that all such honours and advancements are
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:119952:12"/> made by corruption too ordinary instruments of the vilest works of serving Satan, and opposing Christ, and oppressing piety, honesty and innocence, rejoyce not in them as for themselves, nor any way but in subservience to your heavenly rejoycings.</p>
            <p n="4">4. And it should much abate our carnal <hi>joy</hi> to consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that all these things are such, as <hi>may End in mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> and leave the owner in everlasting woe. He that is feasting in purple and fine linnen to day, may be to morrow in remediless torments, and want a drop of water to cool his tongue, <hi>Luke</hi> 16. He that is to day triumphing over mortal enemies, may to morrow be led in triumph to hell fire, and lie in chains of darkness till the judgement of the great day. He that is now <hi>prophecying in the name of Christ, and casting out Devils, and doing many great and wonderful works,</hi> may shortly be condemned at his bar, with a [<hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from me yee workers of iniquity: I never knew you</hi>] Mat. 7. 22. 23. And who would be merry at a feast, that he must cast up again, in griping pain or mortal sickness? You see <hi>now</hi> where the great ones of the world do take their places, and how they are ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired and honoured by men: but you see not where the tide will leave them, and how they shall be used by infernal spirits, if they have not a bettter pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventive and security, then all the renown and digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the world. Be cautelous therefore in your Rejoycing for that, which may end in everlasting sorrows.</p>
            <p>Yea more then so, these outward honours, and successes, may plunge men <hi>deeper in perdition,</hi> then ever they had been without them. And thousands
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:119952:12"/> shall wish that they had never know them; and that they had rather been the lowest and obscurest per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, then by the temptations of prosperity to have been led into that misery. And should you not be very cautelous in your rejoycing in that which you may possibly wish you had never known? You see then the Reasons for the prohibition [<hi>Rejoyce not.</hi>]</p>
            <p n="2">II. But on the contrary, that the <hi>precept [Rejoyce that your names are written in heaven</hi>] is backed with such Reasons from the nature of the thing, as should much excite us to the practise, is a truth so manifest, that a tedious demonstration of it might seem at best unnecessary, and so an error, in these straits of time. 1. What should be Rejoyced in, if not the Lord of life himself, who is the everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting joy and glory of the Saints? If felicity it self cannot make us happy, and life it self is insufficient to quicken us, and the Sun it self cannot illuminate us, it is in vain to expect this light, this life, this happiness and joy, from any other. From others we may have joy <hi>derivatively</hi> at the second hand: but only from God as the <hi>Original</hi> and <hi>first cause.</hi> Other things may be <hi>means</hi> of the <hi>conveyance:</hi> but God is the <hi>matter</hi> of our joy: A <hi>creature</hi> may be <hi>his medicine;</hi> but <hi>he</hi> is our <hi>life and health it self.</hi> Comfort may be <hi>offered</hi> by others; but its he that gives it, others may <hi>direct</hi> us to it, but he <hi>effecteth</hi> it. If <hi>God</hi> be not to be rejoyced in, the affection of <hi>joy</hi> is made in vain: For he is <hi>goodness it self,</hi> and there is nothing lovely or delectable but what is in him. And what is <hi>Heaven,</hi> but the fruition of God?</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:119952:13"/>2. It is <hi>congruous</hi> that we <hi>now Rejoyce, in that which we must Everlastingly rejoyce in. Heaven</hi> is the state of Everlasting joy: and therefore the foresight of it by faith, is the only way to rational solid comfort here. If you knew the <hi>place</hi> in which you should live but an hundred years in earthly pleasures, or the <hi>friend</hi> in whom you should as long have sweet delight, the fore-knowledge of it would make that <hi>place</hi> and <hi>friend,</hi> more delightfull to you then any other. Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table joyes are the shame of man, and shew his levity, or his folly in choosing the things to comfort him, that are insufficient to perform it. But if your hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly interest be the matter of your joy, you may rejoyce to morrow as well as to day, and the next day as well as to morrow, and the next year as well as this. If <hi>prosperity</hi> be your joy, your joy must be <hi>short;</hi> for your worldly prosperity will be so. If <hi>victory,</hi> and <hi>dignity,</hi> and over-topping others be your joy, it will be short; for death is ready to leave the conquerour, the honourable, the Prince, with the conquered, and the meanest subject. If the solem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and feasting of such a day as this should be the greatest matter of your joy, the day will have a night, and the feast an end, and so will your joy. But if <hi>Heaven</hi> be the matter of your joy, you may go on in your rejoycing, and every day may be your fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stivall: For God is the same both yesterday, and to day, and for ever. <hi>You only</hi> have the day that hath no night, and the feast that hath no end, or inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission, unless as it is caused by your errors and mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>apprehensions. There can nothing fall out, of so hurtfull a nature, as to turn your feast into gall and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:119952:13"/> wormwood; for God will be still God, and Christ still your Head, and Heaven will be Heaven, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is of any considerable moment to put into the scales against your happiness. If once you have a God, a Christ, a Heaven to rejoyce in, you may ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionally indulge a constant joy, and may rationally rejoyce in poverty, reproach, contempt and calumny, in imprisonment, banishment, sickness, or in death, as well as in a prosperous state: and you transgress the laws of Reason if you do not.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Rejoyce if your names are written in Heaven; for this is a <hi>Divine,</hi> a <hi>pure,</hi> a <hi>profitable,</hi> and a <hi>warran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> joy. When God and his Ministers <hi>rebuke</hi> your <hi>mirth,</hi> it is not <hi>this holy mirth</hi> that they rebuke, but your dreaming mirth, or waking folly. As we beat down you presumption, but to set up your faith; and beat down mens deceitfull hopes, to prepare them for the hopes that will not fail them, and not to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing them to despair: so do we call you from your frothy, foolish, childish mirth, that we may lead you to the highest joyes. <hi>Here's</hi> joy that you need not be <hi>ashamed</hi> of: of which you can scarcely take too much: of which you need not to repent. Be as joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and merry as you will, if this may but be the matter of your joy. The more you are thus joyfull, the more acceptable to God. It is Satan and not God that is the enemy of this joy; that pleads against it, and fills a Christians mind with groundless scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and doubts, and objections against it. O that our souls, and our assemblies did more abound with this holy joy! And O that Christians understood the excellency and usefulness of it; and would set
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:119952:14"/> themselves more constantly to the promoting and maintaining of it in themselves! Whoever of you is <hi>most joyfull in the Lord,</hi> I dare perswade you to be <hi>more joyfull yet;</hi> and so far should you be from <hi>check<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> your selves for this <hi>holy joy,</hi> that the <hi>rest</hi> of your <hi>duties</hi> should <hi>intend</hi> it, and you should make it your <hi>work</hi> by the help of all Gods Ordinances and mercies to <hi>encrease</hi> it. He is the best Christian, that hath most love, and joy, and gratitude: And he that is best at this, is like to be best in the performance of his other duties; and in the conquest of remaining sins. But more of this in the application.</p>
            <div type="application">
               <p>AND now I am approaching to a closer Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I hope I may suppose that I have removed the Objection that met me in the beginning, and that by this time you see, that I am not unseasonably suppressing your warrantable joy; but 1. preventing that which is unwarrantable, and 2. Shewing you the higher joys, which must animate these, or they will be but dead corrupted things; It is only the <hi>regula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> and the <hi>Exaltation</hi> of your joyes that I am en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring: And for the first, my Text affordeth me so full instruction, that you may see this Observati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on meeting you in the first perusall of the words.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That when the Lord hath vouchsafed us matter of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing in his wonders of Mercy, and our great successes, the best of us are too prone to take up a selfish carnal joy, and have need of Christs prohibition or Caution:</hi> [Rejoyce not in this.]</p>
               <p>The soul is active, and <hi>will</hi> be doing: and there is nothing that it is more naurally inclined to, then <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light.</hi>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:119952:14"/> Something or other (which may be suitable to it, and sufficient to answer its desires) it fain would be rejoycing in. And the <hi>spiritual part</hi> of all our mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies is pure and refined, and too subtile for the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning of our <hi>carnal minds,</hi> and therefore is invisible to the dark ungodly world: and also it is contrary to the interest of the <hi>flesh,</hi> &amp; to the present bent of mans concupiscence; and therefore it is that <hi>spiritual mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies</hi> are not perceived, nor relished by the <hi>flesh,</hi> yea that they are refused (as food by a sick stomack) with enmity and loathing, as if they were judgements or plagues, and not mercies: And hence it is that a <hi>car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal mind</hi> doth as <hi>unwillingly accept</hi> of any mercies of <hi>this sort,</hi> as if it were some heavy service that made God almost beholden to him to accept them. But the <hi>Objects of sense,</hi> the matters of commodity, or honour, or sensuall pleasure, are such, as the <hi>worst</hi> of men are <hi>more eager</hi> after then any other: They are things that flesh it self doth favour, and can judge of, and is naturally (now) too much in love with. And therefore there being too much of this concupiscence yet within us, the best have need, as to be <hi>excited</hi> to the <hi>spiritual</hi> part of their <hi>rejoycing,</hi> so to be <hi>warned and called off</hi> from the <hi>carnal</hi> part. Our successes and our other common mercies, have all of them both a <hi>carnal</hi> and a <hi>spiritual</hi> part: somewhat that is suited to our <hi>bodies,</hi> and somewhat to our <hi>souls:</hi> And as we are all too prone to be sensible and regardfull of our bodily affairs and interests, and too insensible and neglectfull of the matters of our souls; so we can easily pick out so much of providences and mercies, as gratifie and accommodate our flesh; and there
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:119952:15"/> we would stop and know no more; as is if we had no spiritual part to mind, nor the <hi>mercy</hi> any <hi>spiritual part</hi> to be improved. To rejoyce in meer prosperity &amp; suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cess, may be done <hi>without grace,</hi> by <hi>pride,</hi> &amp; <hi>sensuality,</hi> as easily as a drunkard can be mer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y with his cups, or any other sinner in his sin. Think it not needless then to hear this admonition, <hi>Take heed that you rejoyce not carnally in the carkass or outside only of your mercies:</hi> As such an outside-Religion consisting in the shell of duty, without God who is the life and kernell, is not <hi>Religion</hi> indeed, but an hypocriticall, self-decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving shew; so you may turn a day of <hi>Thanksgiving</hi> into a day of <hi>fleshly mirth,</hi> more sinful then a Morrice-dance or May-game, because of the aggravation of conjunct hypocrisie, if you set not a faithfull guard upon your hearts.</p>
               <p>For the <hi>rectifying</hi> therefore and <hi>elevating</hi> of your joyes, I am first to tell you, that <hi>there is matter of far greater joy before you, then all the successes or prosperity of the world;</hi> and <hi>if it be yours,</hi> it may be the matter of <hi>your present joy:</hi> and if <hi>it be not,</hi> yet being freely offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red you, your <hi>acceptance</hi> may quickly <hi>make</hi> it such. Eternal joy and glory is at hand. The door is open: The promise is sure: The way made plain: The helps are many, and safe, and powerfull; You may have the conduct of Christ, and the company of thousands (though the smaller number) if you will go this way; There are passengers every day going on, and entring in; Many that were here the last year, are this year in heaven; yea many that were yesterday on earth, are in heaven to day. It is another kind of assembly and solemnity then this, that <hi>they</hi> are <hi>now</hi> beholding, and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:119952:15"/>
                  <hi>you may</hi> behold. One strain of their celestial melody, doth afford more ravishing sweetness and delight, then all that ever earth could yield. If a day in Gods courts <hi>here,</hi> be better then a thousand in common employments or delights, then sure a day in Heaven is better then ten thousand. That's the Court: and (except the Church which is a garden that hath some celestial plants, and is a seminary or nursery for hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven) this world's the dunghill. <hi>There</hi> all is spiritual, pure and perfect; the soul, the service and the joy: But <hi>here</hi> they are all so mixt with flesh, and therefore so imperfect and impure, that we are <hi>afraid</hi> of our very <hi>comforts,</hi> and are fain upon the review to sorrow over many of our joyes. We come now from cares and troubles to our feasts; and our wedding garments smell of the smoak; and a <hi>secret disquietness</hi> in the midst of our delights, doth tell us, that the <hi>root</hi> of our <hi>troubles</hi> doth remain, and that yet we are not where we should be, and that this is not our rest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing place. We lay by our cares and sorrows on these dayes, with our old clothes, to take them up again to morrow, and alas, they are our ordinary week dayes habit; and it were well if it were only so: But even in laughter the heart is sorrowfull; and in our sweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est joyes we feel such imperfections as threatneth a relapse into our former troubles. But the face of God admitteth no such imperfections in the joy of the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders: There we shall have joy without either feel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or fear of sorrow; and praise without any mixtures of complaint. Our sweetest Love to the Lord of love with feel no bounds, and fear no end. O what un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>speable delights will fill that soul that now walks
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:119952:16"/> mournfully, and feedeth upon complaints and tears! How the Glory of God will make that face to shine for ever, that now looks too dejectedly, and is darkened with griefs, and worn with fears, and dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wears a mourning visage! No trouble can enter into the heavenly Jerusalem: nor is there a mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full countenance in the presence of our King! Self-troubling was the fruit of sin and weakness, of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, mistakes and passion, and therefore is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known in heaven, being pardoned and laid by with our flesh, among the rest of our childish weaknesses and diseases. That poor afflicted wounded soul, that breaths in trouble as its daily air, and thinks it is made up of grief and fear, shall be turned into love and joy, and be unspeakably higher in those heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly delights, then ever it was low in sorrow. O bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed face of the most Glorious God! O happy presence of our glorified Head! O blessed beams of the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal love, that will continually shine upon us! O blessed work! to <hi>behold,</hi> to <hi>love,</hi> to <hi>delight,</hi> and <hi>praise!</hi> O blessed company of holy Angels, and of perfect Saints, so perfectly united, so exactly suited to concord in those felicitating works! where all these are, what sorrow can there be? what relicts of distress, or smallest scars of our antient wounds! Had I but one such friend as the meanest Angel in heaven to converse with, how easily could I spare the courts of Princes, the popular concourse, the learned Acade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and all that the world accounteth pleasure, to live in the sweet and secret converse of such a friend! How delightfully should I hear him discourse of the ravishing love of God, of the Glory of his face, the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:119952:16"/> person of our Redeemer, the continued union of the glorified humane nature with the Divine, and of the Head with all the glorified members, and his influen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces on his imperfect ones below! of the dignity, quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and work of Saints and Angels, and of the manner of their mutual converse? How gladly would I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire from the noise of laughter, the complements of Commick gallants, the clutter and vain-glory of a distracted world, or any the more manly inferiour de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights, to walk with one such heavenly companion? O how the beams of his illuminated intellect, would promote my desired illumination? and the flames of his love to the most Glorious God would reach my heart; what life and heavenly sweetness there would be in all his speeches! that little of Heaven that I have perceived on some of the servants of the Lord, that are conversant above in a life of faith, doth make them more amiable, and their converse much more delectable to me, then all the feastings, musick or meriments in the world. O then, what a world of joy and glory will that be, where we shall not only converse with them that have seen the Lord, and are perfected in the beatifical vision and fruition, but also shall our selves everlastingly behold him, and enjoy him in perfection! That world all true be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers see; They see it by faith in the holy glass which the spirit in the Apostles and Prophets hath set up; And they have the earnest and first fruits of it in themselves, even that spirit by which they are sealed hereunto; That world we are ready to take possessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of; We are almost there; We are but taking our leave of the inhabitants and affairs of earth, and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:119952:17"/> better putting on our heavenly robes, and we are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently there. A few nights more to stay on earth; a few words more to speak to the sons of men; a few more duties to perform, and a few more trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blesom steps to pass, will be a small inconsiderable delay. This room will hold you <hi>now</hi> but an hour longer; and this world but a few hours more; But Heaven will be the dwelling place of Saints, to all eternity. These faces of flesh that we see to day, we shall see but a few times more, if any; But the face of God we shall see for ever. That glory no dismal times shall darken; That joy no sorrow shall inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt; No sin shall forfeit, no enemy shall endanger or take from us; no changes shall ever dispossess us of. And should not a believer then <hi>rejoyce,</hi> that <hi>his name is written in Heaven?</hi> and that every providence wheels him on, and whether the way be fair or foul, its <hi>thither</hi> that he is travelling? O Sirs, if Heaven be better then Vanity and Vexation; if endless joy be better then the laughter of a child that ends in cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and if God be better then a delusory world, you have then greater matters set before you, to be the matter of your joy, then prosperity and success, or any thing that flesh and blood delights in.</p>
               <p>And this being so, I am next in faithfulness to your souls, obliged to call you to enquire, <hi>Whether the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing of this day,</hi> and <hi>the Rejoycing of your lives, do here begin?</hi> Is <hi>God</hi> the <hi>beginning</hi> and the <hi>end</hi> of <hi>all?</hi> O that the Lord would awaken you to perceive, in all your mirth, how nearly it concerneth you, to <hi>know first whether your names are written in heaven?</hi> and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther your <hi>cheifest joy be fetcht from thence.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:119952:17"/>
               <p>Alas, Sirs, its a mhst pittifull sight, to see men frisk about in jollity, with the marks of death and wrath upon them! and to see men so phrantickly merry in their sin, as to forget the misery that will so quickly marre their mirth! and to see men live as quietly and pleasantly as if all were well with them, when they have taken no succesfull care, for their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious souls, nor made any considerable sure provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, for their endless life. Poor sinner! the Lord, who sent me on this message to thee knows, that I envy thee not thy mirth or pleasure, but only would have it better for thee, or have thee set thy mind on better. But let me so farre interrupt thee in thy mirth, as to ask thee, whether thou art sure of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven? or at least, whether thou hast <hi>given diligence</hi> to <hi>make it sure</hi> (2 Pet. 1. 10.) If this night thy soul be called away, canst thou truly say, that thou art an heir of life, and hast laid up thy treasure there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hand? If thou say, that thou <hi>hopest well, and no man can do more,</hi> and thus dost desperately cast thy everlasting life upon a careless venture, I must tell thee first that <hi>Assurance may be had:</hi> would God bid us <hi>Rejoice that our Names are written in Heaven,</hi> if it were a thing that could not by any means be known? would he bid us <hi>give diligence to make our calling and election sure,</hi> if it were a thing that could not by any <hi>diligence</hi> be attained? And I must add, that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumption is no sign of a safe condition: It shall not go well with you because you <hi>imagin</hi> it shall go well: A man in a Dropsie or Consumption will not live, by saying that he hopes he shall not die. Yea more, I must add, that a careless venturousness is a mark of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:119952:18"/> misery: for a man that valueth God and his salvation, cannot put off a matter of such eternall consequence, so sleightly and disregardfully! And a fear and care about your salvation, would be a farre better signe. For the most part, they are safest that fear their dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger: and they are in the saddest case that are never sad at the consideration of their case. It's not your bold and confident conceits, that will open Heaven to you; And therefore I beseech you presently look out for surer grounds of peace then these.</p>
               <p>If you say, <hi>How can it be known to me, whether my Name be written in Heaven or not?</hi> I shall <hi>briefly,</hi> but <hi>satisfactorily</hi> answer it.</p>
               <p>In <hi>generall,</hi> if thou know that thou art one that God hath <hi>promised Heaven</hi> to, thou maist know thy <hi>title,</hi> which is meant by the <hi>writing of thy name in Heaven;</hi> and thou maist know, that this promise shall be made good.</p>
               <p>More particularly, 1. If thou hast had such an effectuall sight of the vanity of earth, and of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly felicity, that Heaven hath the preheminence in thy <hi>practicall estimation,</hi> and <hi>choice,</hi> and thou hast resolved that Heaven or nothing shall be thy <hi>Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piness;</hi> and art so farre at a point with all things un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Sunne, as that thou art resolved to stick closer to Christ then unto them, and whatever it cost thee, to take the fruition of God for ever as thy portion; If upon consideration of the difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Heaven and earth, God and the creatures, eternity and time, thou hast heartily devoted thy self to God, and art willing to be his servant upon the termes that he inviteth thee on, thou maist be
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:119952:18"/> assured that <hi>thy name is written in Heaven,</hi> Matth. 6. 19, 20, 21. &amp; 16. 24, 25, 26. &amp; 13. 45, 46. Luk. 18. 33.</p>
               <p>But if <hi>earth</hi> be the place of thy <hi>highest estimation,</hi> and <hi>choice,</hi> where thou placest thy chief affections, and which thou <hi>adherest to</hi> more <hi>resolutely</hi> then to God, and which thou <hi>wilt not leave</hi> whatever thou lose by it, then as earth hath thy heart, so earth is thy treasure, and thy name is not written in Heaven, but in the dust.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If the <hi>obteining</hi> of Heaven be the principall part of thy care and business, the principall work which thou mindest in the world, its certain that thy name is written in Heaven. <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 1, 2, 3, 4. otherwise not.</p>
               <p n="3">3. If finding thy self lost and filthy in thy sin, thou see the necessity and sufficiency of Christ, and being desirous of his grace and righteousness, dost unfeignedly take him for thy Saviour and Lord, and give up thy self to be healed, and justified, and saved by him, as the only Physicion of souls, thou art then his member, and thy name is written in Heaven, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1. 12. &amp; 3. 16, 18.</p>
               <p n="4">4. If the heavenly nature be most amiable in thy eyes, and the heavenly life be it that thou most desirest: If thou hadst rather be Holy then be unholy, and hadst rather perfectly obey the Lord, then live in sin; and longest to be better, and studiest to live in obedience to the Lord, thy name is in Heaven, and thither thou art passing, and it will be thy reward. But if thou love not Holiness, but hadst rather be excused from it, and live in thy sins,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:119952:19"/> thou art as yet no heir of Heaven, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. 19. &amp; 12. 26. <hi>Psal.</hi> 1. &amp; 119. 11.</p>
               <p n="5">5. If thy <hi>name be written in Heaven,</hi> thou hast a <hi>speciall love to the heirs of Heaven:</hi> and the more of Heaven thou findest in their hearts and lives, the more amiable they are unto thee, and the sweeter is their converse, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. 14. <hi>Psal.</hi> 15. 4.</p>
               <p>I shall name no more: These Evidences are sure. By these you may know while you sit here in these seats, yea if you lay in the darkest dungeon, that you are the heirs of Heaven, and your names are there.</p>
               <p>But where there is no such work, no high estima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Heaven and resolution for it, no mortification or conquest of the world, no prevalent care and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence for Heaven, no resignation of the soul to Christ, that by faith and holiness we might follow him to that glory, no love to holiness, and no delight in the heirs of Heaven, such persons are yet aliens to the heavenly nature and inheritance, and cannot rejoice that their names are written in Heaven.</p>
               <p>And now I have set the glass before you, I earnest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly intreat you, that you will here seriously view the complexion of your souls. It more neerly concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth you to know whether your names are written in Heaven, and where it is that you must dwell for ever, than to know how to manage your trades and busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, or to know whether you shall stirre from this place alive, or ever see another day. O sirs take heed of living in self-deceit, till your trying and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering time is past. This is it that your enemy aims at: he will do all that malice and subtilty can do, to keep such matters from your sober thoughts, or to
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:119952:19"/> make you groundlesly presume that you are safe, or securely to cast your souls upon a desperate venture, under pretence of trusting in Christ; till he hath you where he would have you; and then he will himself take off the veil, and let you know that you had time and light to have acquainted you with your disease and misery, while you might have had a free, and sure, and full remedy. Then you shall know that it was long of your self-deceit if you would not understand and beleeve in time, that <hi>if you lived after the flesh you should die</hi>] Rom. 8. 13. and [<hi>that it is the pure in heart that shall see God,</hi> Matth. 5. 8. [<hi>Know ye not that the unrighteous shall not inherit the Kingdom of God? be not deceived: neither fornicators, nor idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, nor adulterers, nor effeminate, nor thieves, nor covetous, nor drunkards, nor revilers, nor extortion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, shall inherit the Kingdom of God,</hi> 1 Cor. 6. 9, 10. <hi>For this ye know, that no whoremonger, nor unclean person, nor covetous man who is an idolater, hath any inheritance in the Kingdom of Christ and of God: Let no man deceive you with vain words; for because of these things cometh the wrath of God on the children of disobedience,</hi> Ephes. 5. 5, 6.] And can any thing justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the Rejoicing of men, in so sad a state?</p>
               <p>Give me leave therefore to make a little closer application, of the severall parts of my Text, to the severall sorts of persons whom they do concern. And first to all <hi>that yet are not become the heirs of Heaven: Rejoice not though Devils were subject to you,</hi> till your souls are <hi>subject</hi> to him that bought them: Rejoice not though you had conquered all the world, and had your wills of all your adversaries, as long as you are
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:119952:20"/> conquered by your fleshly lusts, and Satan leads you captive at his will, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 25, 26. Rejoice not though you had all the riches of the earth, as long as you are void of the riches of grace, and have nothing to do with the riches of glory. Rejoice not though all men should honour you, and bow to you, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim your fame, as long as you are the drudges of the Devill and the flesh, and the God of Heaven pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimeth you his enemies, and resolveth on your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction, if you do not soundly and seasonably re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, <hi>Luk.</hi> 19. 27. &amp; 13. 3, 5.</p>
               <p>Be not offended with me, that on a day of Thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving <hi>I thus farre forbid you to rejoyce;</hi> For, it is not <hi>you</hi> that are qualified for it, or have any part or fellowship in this business, being in the gall of bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terness and bonds of your iniquity, your hearts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not right in the sight of God. Though the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitation be generall, it supposeth that you come pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared: and therefore even he that calls men to his joyes, will find out him that hath not on the wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding garment, and will bind him and cast him into outer darkness, where shall be weeping and gnashing of teeth, <hi>Matth.</hi> 22. 12, 13.] 1. Alas Sirs, if <hi>God</hi> would <hi>allow</hi> you to <hi>Rejoyce,</hi> how willingly could I allow it you? But hear whether he approve it, <hi>Jam.</hi> 5. 1, 2, 3. <hi>Go to now ye rich men, weep and howl for the miseries that are coming on you: your riches are cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, and your garments motheaten, your gold and silver is cankered, and the rust of them shall be a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness against you, and shall eat your flesh as it were fire: yee have heaped treasure together for the last dayes.</hi>] Luk. 6. 24, 25, 26. <hi>Woe unto you that are rich</hi> (if you
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:119952:20"/> have no better riches;) <hi>for ye have received your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solation. Woe unto you that are full, for ye shall hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger: Woe unto you that laugh now, for ye shall mourn and weep: Woe unto you when all men shall speak well of you,</hi> &amp;c.] You may find your lesson, <hi>Joel 2. 12, 13. Thus saith the Lord; Turn ye, even to me, with all your hearts, with fasting, and with weeping, and with mourning, and rent your hearts.</hi> You see what God calls such men to. And if <hi>he</hi> allow you not to <hi>rejoyce</hi> till you are Converted, if I or any man should flatter or cheat you into joy, it would be but a curse to you, and not a benefit.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Were your <hi>Joy</hi> but <hi>Reasonable</hi> I would not dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage it. But a mad mans laughter is no very lovely spectacle to your selves. And I appeal to all the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son in the world, whether it be <hi>Reasonable</hi> for a man to live in Mirth, that is yet unregenerate, and under the curse and wrath of God, and can never say, in the midst of his greatest pomp or pleasure, that he is sure to be an hour out of hell; and may be sure he shall be there for ever, if he die before he have a new, a holy and a heavenly nature; though he should die with laughter in his face, or with a jest in his mouth, or in the boldest presumption that he shall be saved, yet as sure as the word of God is true, he will find himself everlastingly undone, as soon as ever his soul is departed from his body, and he sees the things that he would not believe. Sirs, Is it ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall to dance in Satans fetters, at the brink of hell, when so many hundred diseases are all ready, to marre the mirth, and snatch away the guilty soul, and cast it into endless desparation? I exceedingly pitty the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:119952:21"/> godly in their unwarrantable melancholly griefs; and much more an ungodly man that's bleeding under his wounds of conscience: But a man that is merry in the depth of misery, is more to be pittied then he. Me thinks it is one of the most pittifull sights in all the world, to see a man ruffle it out in bravery, and spend his precious time in pleasures, and melt into sensuall foolish mirth, that is a stranger to God, and within a step of endless woe! When I see their pomp, and feasting, and attendance, and hear their laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and insipid jests, and the fidlers at their doors or tables, and all things carried as if they had made sure of Heaven, it sadneth my heart to think, Alas how little do these sinners know the state that they are in, the God that now beholdeth them, the change that they are neer! How little do they think of the flames that they are hasting to, and the outcries and lamentations that will next ensue.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Your Mirth is <hi>disingenuous</hi> and <hi>dishonest,</hi> as long as you are without a title to Heaven: You slight the Lord, that can find such matters of rejoicing, when you have not his favour to rejoice in, and are under his displeasure! while you are refusing Christ, abusing grace, resisting the spirit, serving the flesh, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing your own souls, it cannot be an <hi>honest</hi> or <hi>inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuous</hi> thing for such as you to live in joy.</p>
               <p n="4">4. If your <hi>mirth</hi> were truly <hi>Honourable</hi> to you, it were the more excusable. But to laugh in sin and misery, and make merry so neer your endless woe, is a greater shame to your understandings, then to make sport to set your house on fire: This is the laughter of which <hi>Solomon</hi> might well say, <hi>Thou art
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:119952:21"/> mad,</hi> and the mirth of which he saith, <hi>what doth it? Eccl.</hi> 2. 2.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Would thy <hi>mirth</hi> do thee <hi>any good</hi> we would not discourage it; yea if it did not do thee <hi>harm.</hi> But O how many are now in sorrow, by the means of their unseasonable sinfull mirth? They are too jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cund to hear the Preacher, or their consciences, or to observe the checks and motions of Gods Spirit: or to spend now and then an hour in retired sober thoughts of their everlasting state. Should we but presume to call them to exercise their reason, and mind them of these most needfull things, and tell them, <hi>O poor distracted mortals, your time is given you for greater things, then to fiddle, and dance, and drink, and jeast, and praie, and complement it away!</hi> Should we not be thought morose, or melancholly, or fanaticks; and should we not have some such answer as their ancestors in <hi>Sodome</hi> gave to <hi>Lot?</hi> Gen. 19. 9. [<hi>stand back: this one fellow came in to sojourn, and and he will needs be a judg: we will deal worse with thee then with them,</hi>] wee'l take a course with these controllers. Alas, it is this foolish mirth, that casteth mens <hi>reason</hi> and <hi>consciences</hi> asleep, and drowns the voice of sober words, so that God himself cannot be heard. Could we but get men to retired sober<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness and seriousness, we should hope that we might find a friend within them, and that we speak to <hi>men,</hi> and that reason would take part with the most rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable motions that are made to them from the Lord.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Lastly, Would your groundless <hi>mirth endure,</hi> we would not say so much against it. But, alas, to be
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:119952:22"/> merry for a day, and then to lie in misery for ever, is a thing deserving no encouragement. We see its a <hi>merry world</hi> with many that have least cause of mirth: but <hi>how long will they continue it?</hi> To see a man laugh, and play, and feast in a chariot that drives on so fast to death; in a vessell that is in so swift a stream that ends in the gulf of endless horrour, is a dolefull sight. O how quickly will that merry coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance turn sad; those proud looks be turned to an earthly paleness; and those wanton eyes be moul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered to dust, and leave the empty holes, to warn the next spectators to use his eyes more wisely while he hath them? How quickly will these same sensuall persons, exchange their mirth for sighs and groans, and endless torments, and fruitless lamentations, when they shall have everlasting leisure to peruse their lives, and to consider of their ways, which now there is no perswading them to consider of? Who can encourage such hurtfull and unseasonable mirth as this? <hi>Hos. 9. 1. Rejoice not O Israel for joy, as other people, for thou host gone a whoring from thy God.] Rejoice not in a thing of nought,</hi> Amos 6. 13. Much less in the sufferings of your bretheren; see <hi>Obad.</hi> 12. and least of all in any hurt that befalls the Church. If enmity to holiness, and exalted impiety should take occasion to triumph; we answer as <hi>Mich. 7. 8, 9. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joice not against me O mine enemy; when I fall, I shall arise: when I sit in darkness the Lord shall be a light unto me: I will bear the indignation of the Lord, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause I have sinned against him, untill he plead my cause, and execute judgment for me: he will bring me forth to the light, and I shall behold his righteousness.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:119952:22"/>
               <p>If you think I have stood too long on the first part of my Text, it is not to <hi>rebuke</hi> your <hi>holy joy,</hi> but only to <hi>promote it,</hi> and <hi>repress</hi> that <hi>carnall joy,</hi> which is more destructive to it, then sorrow it self. As you must [<hi>seek first the Kingdom of God and its Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousness,</hi> and then <hi>other things shall be added to you,</hi>] (Matth. 6. 33.) so must you <hi>rejoyce first</hi> in the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Heaven,</hi> and the <hi>Righteousness</hi> that is the way thereto, and then you may <hi>add a moderate rejoicing</hi> in the things below, in a due subordination thereunto. You have the summe in the words of the Holy ghost, <hi>Jer.</hi> 9. 23, 24. [<hi>Thus saith the Lord, Let not the wise man glory in his wisdome, neither let the mighty man glory in his might; let not the rich man glory in his riches; but let him that glorieth glory in this, that he understandeth and knoweth me, that I am the Lord,</hi> &amp;c.]</p>
               <p n="2">2. My next address must be to them, whose <hi>names are written in Heaven,</hi> and that with a twofold Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Rejoice that your names are written in Heaven.</hi> Its <hi>you,</hi> Christians, that <hi>joy</hi> of right belongs to. Little know the <hi>lovers of pleasure, more than God,</hi> that they lose a thousand fold more pleasure than they win: and that by running from a holy life for pleasure, they run from the fire into the water for heat, and from the Sun into a dungeon for light. O shew the unbelieving world by your rejoicing, how they are mistaken in their choice. Be ashamed that an empty sott, and one that must be for ever a firebrand in hell, should live a more joyfull life than you! O do not so wrong your Lord, your faith, your endless joys, as
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:119952:23"/> to walk in heaviness, and cast away the joy of the Lord which is your strength, and to be still complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, when those that are prepared for the slaughter, are as frolick as if the bitterness of death were past. It's well that you have so much life, as to feel your sicknesses: but it is not well, that because you are yet diseased, the life of grace and of glory should be so uneffectuall to your comfort. And yet alas, how common is it, to see the most miserable frisk and fleere, while the heirs of life are sinfully vexing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves with the inordinate fears of death! Lift up thy head Christian and remember, whence came thy gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, even thy least desires, and whither do they tend! Where is thy Father, and thy Head, and the most of thy dear companions? where is it that thou must live to all eternity? Doth it beseem a companion of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, a member of Christ, a child of God, an heir of Heaven, to be grieved at every petty cross, and to lay by all the sense of their felicity, because some trifle of the world falls cross to their desires and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity? Is it seemly for one, that must be everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stingly as full of joy, as the Sun is full of light, to live in such a self-troubling, drooping state, as to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace Religion, and frighten away the ungodly from the doors of grace, that by your joyfull lives might be provokt to enter? I know as to your happinesse the matter is not comparatively great; because if mistakes and the Devils malice, should keep you sad here a hundred years, yet Heaven will wipe away all tears, and those joys will be long enough when they come: and as the joy of the ungodly, so the sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows of the humble upright soul, will be but for a
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:119952:23"/> moment. And though you weep and lament when the world rejoyceth, as their joy shall be turned into sorrow, so your sorrow shall be turned into joy, and your joy shall no man take from you. But in the mean time, is it not shame and pity, that you should live so unanswerable to the mercies of the Lord? that <hi>you</hi> should sinfully grieve the comforting spirit, by the wilfull grieving of your selves; and that you should peevishly cast away your precious mercies, when you so much need them, by reason of the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of a vexations world, which you cannot avoid? that <hi>you,</hi> even <hi>you</hi> that are saved by the Lord, should still be questioning it, or unthankfully denying his great salvation, and so much hinder the salvation of others? For the Lords sake Christians, and for your souls sake, and in pity to the ungodly, yeeld not to the tempter, that would trouble you, when he cannot damne you? Is God your Father, and Christ your Saviour, and the Spirit your sanctifier, and Heaven your home? and will you make all (for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent) as nothing to you, by a causless obstinate de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall? If you are in doubt, let not meer passionate <hi>fears</hi> be heard; and let not the Devill, the enemy of your peace be heard: but peruse your evidences, and still remember as the summe of all, that the <hi>will is the man; and what you would be, that you are, before the Lord.</hi> If you cannot see the sincerity of your hearts, go to your faithfull able guides, and open the case to them, and let not passion prevail against the Scripture and Reason which they bring. Yea if in your trouble you cannot by all their helps, perceive the uprightness of your hearts, I must tell you, you
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:119952:24"/> may stay your selves much upon their judgment of your state. Though it cannot give you full assurance it may justly help to silence much of your self-accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sations, and give you the comfort of probability. If a Physician, that feels not what you feel, shall yet upon your speeches, and other evidences, tell you that he is confident your disease is not mortall, nor conteineth any cause of fear, you may rationally be much encouraged by his judgement, though it give you no certainty of life. As wicked men through contempt, so many godly people through melancholy, do lose much of the fruit of the office of the Ministry: which lieth much in this assisting men, to judg of the life or death of their souls. <hi>Alas,</hi> say they, <hi>he feels not what I feel: he is used to judg charitably, and he knoweth not me so well as I know my self.</hi> But when you have <hi>told him</hi> faithfully (as you do your Physician) what it is that <hi>you know by your self,</hi> he is able to pass a farre sounder judgment of your life, or death, then your selves can do, for all your feeling. For he knows better what those sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptoms signifie, and what is used to be the issue of such a case as yours. Be not then so proud or wilfull, as to refuse the judgment of your faithfull Pastors, about the state of your souls, in a confidence on your own.</p>
               <p>And look not for more, as necessary to your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts, then God hath made necessary. Is it nothing to have a <hi>Title to eternall life,</hi> unless you be also as <hi>holy as you desire?</hi> Yea is it nothing to have a <hi>desire</hi> to be <hi>more holy?</hi> Will you have <hi>no comfort,</hi> as long as you have <hi>distractions</hi> or <hi>dullness,</hi> or such like im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:119952:24"/> in duty? And till you have no disease of soul to trouble you, that is, till you have laid by flesh, and arrived at your perfect joy? Dare not to disobey the voice of God: <hi>Psal. 32. 11. Be glad in the Lord, and rejoice ye righteous; and shout for joy all ye that are upright in heart.</hi> 1 Thess. 5. 16. <hi>Rejoice evermore.</hi> Let it be something that <hi>Heaven</hi> cannot weigh down, that shall suppress thy joy? Art thou in poverty? and is not Heaven sufficient riches? Art thou in dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace? and shalt thou not have honour enough in Heaven? Art thou in danger from the injustice or the wrath of man? and is he not Almighty that hath undertaken to justifie thee? <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 33, 34. Dost thou languish under pining sicknesses? and is there not everlasting health in Heaven? Art thou weak in knowledg, in memory, in grace, in duty? troubled with uncommanded thoughts and passions? and was it not so on earth with all that are now in Heaven? O Christians make conscience of obeying this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand: <hi>Rejoice that your names are written in Heaven.</hi> Did you but know how God approveth such rejoicing, and how much it pleaseth him above your pining sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows; and how it strengtheneth the soul, and sweetneth duty, and easeth suffering, and honoureth Religion, and encourageth others, and how suitable it is to Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spell grace, and to your high relations and ends, and how much better it serves to subdue the very sins that trouble you, than your fruitless self-weakning com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plainings do; I say, did you well consider all these things, it would <hi>sure</hi> revive your drooping spirits.</p>
               <p>And do not say now, [<hi>I would rejoice if I were sure that my name were written in Heaven: but I am not
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:119952:25"/> sure.</hi>] For 1. <hi>Who is it long of, that you are not sure?</hi> you <hi>may be sure</hi> that he hath <hi>valueth and seeketh Heaven as better then earth,</hi> and that <hi>loveth the holy way to Heaven,</hi> and the <hi>most heavenly people,</hi> is indeed an <hi>heir of Heaven;</hi> and you <hi>may be sure,</hi> if you <hi>will,</hi> that <hi>this is your own case:</hi> and yet you say, <hi>you are not sure that your names are written in Heaven.</hi> If God give you his grace and you deny it, will you therefore de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny your right to glory, and make one sin the excuse for another?</p>
               <p n="2">2. And if you <hi>are not sure,</hi> is it nothing to have your <hi>probabilities,</hi> and <hi>hopes,</hi> and the <hi>judgment of your able faithfull Pastors,</hi> that your souls are in a safe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition? We dare not say so to the careless world, nor to the most of men, as we do to you.</p>
               <p>Especially take heed lest <hi>melancholy habituate you to fears and griefs;</hi> and then <hi>Religion must bear the blame,</hi> and <hi>you undergo a calamitous life,</hi> though you are the heirs of Heaven. To this end 1. Use not musing serious thoughts beyond the strength of your brain and intellect. 2. Place not too much of your Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion in the perusals and study of your hearts: but (for such as are inclined to melancholy) it is the fruitfull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est way, to be much in expending duties abroad, and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring to do good to others: such duties have less of self, and as much of God, and divert the troubling melancholly thoughts, and bring in more comfort by way of reward, then is usually got by more direct en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring after comfort. 3. Use not too much solita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riness and retiredness: man is a sociable creature: and as his duty lyeth much with others, so his comfort ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in the same way as his duty. 4. Take heed of
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:119952:25"/> worldly sorrows: and therefore of overvaluing world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things. 5. Take heed of idleness, or of think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the duty of holiness are all that you have to mind: but make conscience of being diligent in a particular calling: which diverts the hurtfull trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling thoughts, and is pleasing unto God. 6. Take not every sickness of your souls for death: but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in that life which enableth you to be troubled at your diseases. Keep under melancholy by these meanes (and the advice of the Physician) and you will escape a very great hinderance to this high and holy duty of <hi>heavenly rejoycing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. But you think perhaps that I have all this while forgotten the duty proper to the day. No: but I was not fit to speak for it, nor you fit to hear and practise it, till the <hi>impediment of carnall rejoycing</hi> was <hi>removed,</hi> and till we had <hi>begun</hi> with <hi>heavenly joy.</hi> It is <hi>Heaven</hi> that must <hi>animate all</hi> our comforts. They are so <hi>far</hi> sweet as Heaven is in them, and no further. Now therefore if you <hi>first rejoyce</hi> for your <hi>heavenly interest,</hi> I dare safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly then perswade you, to rejoyce in the mercies which we are, to be thankfull for this day. And though some of them are but yet in the birth, if not in the womb, and we are yet uncertain what they'le prove, that will not excuse us for any un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfullness; for the first conception or infancy of our mercies. And though Satan seek to get ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage by them, that will not excuse us for our overlooking the mercie in it self. And though there are yet abundance of fears and troubles, on the hearts of many of Christs servants through the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:119952:26"/> Land, we cannot by any such accidents be excused, from the thankfull observation of the workings of the Lord. All mercies on earth even spirituall mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, have their mixtures of trouble and their imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections: but must not therefore be denied or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenuated. And though many that are dear to us, smarting by the change, will be offended and grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved at our most moderate thanksgiving; we must not therefore offend the Lord, by our disregardfullness of his works.</p>
               <p>There are these things to be commemorated by us this day, which I dare not overlook. 1. That <hi>God</hi> hath so honoured his <hi>justice</hi> and <hi>impartiality,</hi> as to shew how he hateth sin in whomsoever. And indeed the <hi>justice</hi> of God it self would seem more <hi>amiable</hi> to us, were we not so <hi>selfish,</hi> as to think hardly of all thats hurtfull unto <hi>us. Justice</hi> demonstrateth the <hi>holinesse</hi> of God, and all the appearances of his holinesse are lovely in themselves.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That the holy God hath <hi>disowned heresie</hi> and <hi>divisions</hi> on the one side, as well as <hi>impiety</hi> and <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneness</hi> on the other: and that his wisdome thought meet, to acquaint us <hi>experimentally</hi> with the hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullnesse of both, and our danger of both, as he did in former ages of the Church. We first found the serpentine malice of the ungodly, and God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered us, when they would have swallowed us up. But while we only heard and read of <hi>heresie</hi> and <hi>schisme,</hi> and that too often abusively applyed, to many of the most peaceable servants of the Lord, we understood not the mischiefe of those evills; but were ready to take the very names, to be but
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:119952:26"/> the reproaches of piety it self. But God saw meet to let out a flood of this sort of calamities, and to suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer heresie to disgrace it self by its unrighteous fruits, that by those fruits we might the better know it. We never knew before how much we are beholding to him, for saving us from <hi>this sort</hi> of evils; and should never have sufficiently hated them, if we had not smarted by them.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It is a mercy to be thankfull for, that thus the Church is notably fortified, against ever relapsing into heresie or schisme for the time to come.</p>
               <p n="4">4. And that the frailties of men professing god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liness, having so lamentably appeared, they are taught to take heed of spirituall pride, and to know and distrust themselves, and not to be high-minded, but to fear.</p>
               <p n="5">5. It is a very great mercy, for which I must pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fess I was thankfull from the first appearance of it;<note place="margin">We kept this Thanksgiving voluntarily in <hi>Worcestershire,</hi> by Agreement among the As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sociated Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters, as we do here this day. See the Agreement published by the weekly Mercury.</note> that so many that I hope are dear to God, have the advantage of his frowns to further their conviction, and repentance, and salvation. As prosperity was the temptation, by which ambition got advantage, and providence mis-understood was pleaded, against the holy rule: what a mercy is it that providence also should undeceive them, and vindicate it self, and teach men hereafter by the example of this age, to stay till the end, before they take the sense of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, or rather to adhere to the holy word, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the longest liver shall be too short-lived to see the end, so far as to furnish him for such an interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation? And therefore that word that is the glass in which we can <hi>foresee</hi> the end, must be our guide.
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:119952:27"/> I had rather have my friend poor and penitent, than wealthy and impenitent; and rather in a prison, than in the chains of pride: and am glad that God hath taken away the snare that brought so many souls to so sad a pass; and hath undeceived them in part, that had carnall thoughts of the happiness of Saints, and lookt for temporall reign and dignity; forgetting that rich men must pass through a needles eye to Heaven, and that lowliness, meekness, humility, patience, forbearing, forgiving, self-denial, contempt of this world, and living all upon things unseen, is the life that Christ by his doctrine and example taught us, and how ill prosperity befriendeth these. I am in far more hope to see many <hi>Peters go out and weep bitterly,</hi> then I was when they <hi>prospered</hi> in a <hi>sinfull way.</hi> And if yet any be so far unhumbled, as to deny it to have been a <hi>sinfull way,</hi> I am in far greater hope of their conviction now, then hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. In their greatness few durst tell them of their crimes: and those of us that did it, were volumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nously reproached, threatned, calumniated, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presented as turbulent to the world: (it being usuall with base spirited men, to take the judgement of the greatest for their rule, and to think all suffering to be just and dishonourable, that is inflicted by such as few dare contradict.) But now I hope plain dealing may recover many that before lived under flatteries, and were above reproof. I must profess that my hopes of the saving of many that are dear to me, by the furtherance of this providence, is matter of so much thankfulness to me, that were I sure to suffer with them, I would yet give thanks.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:119952:27"/>6. It is matter of thanksgiving to me, that God hath so far owned an unanimous, painfull, faithfull Ministry, (for all their many sad infirmities,) as <hi>first</hi> to break the <hi>profane</hi> opposers of them, and then to <hi>scatter</hi> the adversaries on the <hi>other side.</hi> Ever since I heard it so fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar among them, to call Christs faithfullest servants by so many reproachfull names, as Priests (in scorn) Pres-biters, Drivines, Jack-Presbyters, Blackcoats, Pulpeteers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and theirs friends, <hi>Priest-ridden;</hi> to suffer Quakers openly in the streets to revile them as Deceivers, Doggs, Wolves, Hirelings, false-Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, Lyars, and all the names that hell could teach them, I waited in fear for the Judgments of the Lord; which he hath executed in our sight, and caused us to know, that his delayes are no desertions of his ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, nor justification of our revilers. And let it stand as a warning to <hi>you</hi> that have <hi>seen</hi> it, and <hi>you</hi> that have executed the punishments of God, upon the reproachers, that you take heed of falling into the same crime, and dashing on the rock on which they have been broken; but let all <hi>England</hi> hear and fear, and do no more so malignantly or presumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously.</p>
               <p>And O that we the unworthy Ministers of Christ may remember, that we are not vindicated and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered to contend, or to imitate our afflicters, in seeking greatness to our selves, not to live in idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and neglect the souls committed to our care.</p>
               <p n="7">7. It is very great cause of Thankfullness in my eyes, that from first to last God hath been so tender of the honour of his unanimous sober people, and his cause, and of the innocency and consciences of his
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:119952:28"/> servants; as to execute his afflictions mostly by the hands of erring men; and to keep the rest by impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonments, seclusions, and other means, so farre from all appearance of consent, to irregularities: and that at last he hath put an opportunity into their hands, to declare to the world, their innocency in the things, with which they were reproached: and that while pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane opposers of Religion, did boast and vapour, and swear, and curse, and drink healths for his Majesties restitution, it is <hi>those whom they reproached,</hi> that have <hi>silently</hi> and <hi>effectually</hi> accomplisht it, and that with <hi>speed,</hi> as soon as they had power.</p>
               <p n="8">8. It is some matter of Thankfullness to me, that whereas to our perpetuall shame, we could not in so many years compose the disagreements in Church affairs among us, we are not altogether without hope, that agreement may be now more effectually procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; not only because that carnall advantages, that hindred it with some, are taken from them, and suffering will dispose some more to peace; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause we are <hi>perswaded</hi> the <hi>disposition,</hi> and we are <hi>sure</hi> the <hi>interest</hi> of his Majesty standeth, for our re-conciliation and unity. And verily we are the most inexcusable people in the world, if our own long and sad experiences do not resolve us to do the utmost in that work our selves, which if we are not horridly proud and wilfull, in easie to accomplish.</p>
               <p n="9">9. And its matter of Thanksgiving, that <hi>God hath been all along so wonderfully seen in the work;</hi> which makes us hope, that the issue will yet be for our good. The <hi>first sparks</hi> that set fire on the last foundation, are yet <hi>much unknown,</hi> but were <hi>so little</hi> as makes it
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:119952:28"/> the more strange. The wonderfull whirlwind that sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly finished the subversion, was marvellous, though sad, because of the wickedness of men. The introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of the remnant of the Members; <hi>the</hi> stop that was given them, when they had voted in a Committee, a liberty in Religion, that excepted not Popery: the casting of them out, by those that set them up; the discoveries of the fallaciousness of some of their chiefs, that then were tempted into a compliance with the Army, and were fabricating a new form of a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth: the breaking of them and of the Army, in part by the returning Members: the unexpected stop that was given first to their proceedings by his excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency in the North: the expeditiousness, the constancy, the unanimity and strange successfullness of that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, that an Army that thought themselves only fit to be the Nations security for liberty and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and were thought necessary to be entailed upon us to that end; that were so heightned in their own and other mens esteem, by their many and wonderfull successes, should in a moment (we scarce know how) fly all into pieces, as a Granado that's fired. The <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> at the same time should be so strangely and easi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reduced, and that by sober faithfull hands, and by so few, and with such speed! That this famous City should be so unanimously excited to concurre so emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently, and contribute so very much to the success: that his Excellency should conquer without any blows; and all be dispatched that since is done, with no considerable resistance; all this and much more, do make us wonder at the hand of God. And seldom is there so wonderfull an appearance of the Lord, but
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:119952:29"/> it holds forth matter that's <hi>amiable</hi> as well as <hi>admirable</hi> to his Church.</p>
               <p>Lastly, That all this is done with little or no effu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion at all of blood, when so much blood was shed in the foregoing changes, advanceth the wonder to a greater height. And I hope his Majesty and the two Houses of Parliament will take notice, how God hath gone before them in a tender and unbloody change, and will not hearken to them that protest against <hi>revenge,</hi> while they would use it under the name of <hi>justice.</hi> When the wheel of providence turneth so fast, if all that have the advantage of executing their wils under the name of justice, should <hi>take</hi> their advantage, you know what <hi>names</hi> and <hi>suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings</hi> multitudes of the usefullest Members in such Nations, in the severall vicissitudes must <hi>incurr,</hi> to the detriment of the Commonwealth and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours.</p>
               <p n="3">3. You see what cause we have of thankfulness: but I must tell you that this (as all inferiour mercies) are imperfect things, and being but <hi>meanes</hi> to great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er <hi>matters,</hi> (the heavenly interest first treated on) they are no further significant or valuable, then they have some tendency to their end. And I must fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tell you, that it's much committed into the hands of man, (under God) whether such beginnings shall have a happy or unhappy end. If <hi>Christ</hi> become to many <hi>a stumbling stone,</hi> and be <hi>set for the fall of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in Israel,</hi> (Luk. 2. 34.) and if the Gospel it self prove the <hi>savour of death</hi> to some, no wonder if it be yet possible and too easie, for a sinfull Land, to turn these forementioned mercies and successes, into most
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:119952:29"/> heavy judgements, and to rob themselves of all the honour and the benefit. And therefore <hi>above all,</hi> for the Lords sake, and for a poor tired yet hoping Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions sake, and for the sake of the cause of Christ through the world, I beseech you, all from the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est to the lowest, that you will be awakened to an holy vigilancy, and look about you in your severall places, lest the enemy of Christ and you, should play his after-game more successfully then now you can foresee: and lest the return of a sinfull Nation to their vomit, should make the end yet worse than the beginning. It is not enough to have begun: the fruit of all is yet behind. I must here deal plainly with you, however it be taken, lest I be charged with unfaithfulness, at the dreadfull Tribunal to which both you and I are hastening. If these beginnings, through your neglects, or any others that have been the instruments, should now be turned to the revive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and strengthening of prophaneness, and maligni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty against the holy wayes of God; to the introducti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of meer formality in Religion; to the casting out, or weakening the hands of the faithfull Ministers in the Land; to the destruction of order and Discipline in the Churches, to the suppression of orderly and edifying meetings for mutuall assistance in the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of salvation; or to the cherishing of ignorance or Popery in the people; it will blast the glory of all that you have done, and turn the mercy into gall. Believe it, the interest of Christ and holiness, will be found at last the surest ground, for any Prince to build his interest upon: And the owning of corrupt and
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:119952:30"/> contrary interests, that engage men in quarrels with the interest of Christ, is it that hath undone so many Princes and States already, that it should make the greatest learn at last, to account it their highest ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to be the servants of the King of Saints, and to devote their power to the accomplishment of his will. I need not tell you, that it's the sober, godly, conscio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable sort of men, that know what they do, and why, that will be the honour of their Governours, and the usefullest of their subjects, and not the barbarous ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant rabble, that understand not what belongs to the pleasing of God, the happiness of themselves, the good of the Commonwealth, or the honour of their King. And do you not think that remisness (to say no worse) of Magistrates that should restrain the insolencies of such, is not a great dishonour to our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and a great temptation to many in the Countrey, that stand at a distance from the fountain of affairs, to continue their fears lest we have changed for the worse? Put your selves in their cases, and tell me whether you could with equall cheerfullness keep this day, if you were used as many able, faithfull Ministers and people are in the Cities and Countreys of the Land, who have their persons assaulted, their win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows battered, their ministrations openly reviled, and that go in danger of their lives, from the bruitish rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that were formerly exasperated by the Magistrates punishing them, or the Ministers reproof, or crossing them in their sins. As Physicions are judged of, not so much by the <hi>excellency</hi> of their <hi>remedies,</hi> as by their <hi>success,</hi> and the people think of them as they see the patients <hi>live</hi> or <hi>die;</hi> so will they do by <hi>your great-per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances</hi>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:119952:30"/> which you mention before the Lord this day. Should they prove to the <hi>suppression of serious god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liness,</hi> and the <hi>setting up of the wicked of the Land,</hi> I need not tell you <hi>what a name it will leave unto the actors to all generations.</hi> But if you vigilantly improve them (as you have given us abundant reason to expect,) and the issue shall be <hi>the healing concord of the Churches, the curbing of profaneness, the promoting of a plain and serious Ministry, and of the diligent ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the Lord;</hi> this is it that will make your Names immortall that have been the happy instruments of so blessed a work! How joyfully then will the subjects commemorate, the happy introduction of their So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign? With what love and honour will they hear his Name? How readily will they obey him? How heartily will they pray for him? How precious will <hi>your</hi> memory be? and this will be numbered among the wonderfull deliverances of <hi>England.</hi> If Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness be persecuted or made a common scorn in the Land, the holy God will vindicate his honour, and make their Names a scorn and curse that shall procure it. But if you exalt him, he will exalt you: Protect his Lambs and he will be your Protector. He is with you while you are with him, 2 <hi>Chron. 15. 2. Those that honour him he will honour; and those that despise him shall be lightly esteemed,</hi> 1 Sam. 2. 30.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>